{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Anthony, Duke of Brabant, arrived late to this battle, where he used a trumpeter's flag to make a surcoat. One leader at this battle ordered the mass execution of prisoners after Ysembart [[EE-zem-barht]] stole the victor's crown from a baggage train. This battle, which occurred on St. Crispin’s Day, led to the marriage of Charles VI's daughter and its victor in the Treaty of Troyes [[TWAH]]. For ten points, name this victory for Henry V during the Hundred Years’ War, which included heavy use of longbows.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Agincourt ]",
        "Battle of Azincourt",
        "be lenient on pronunciation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1968, this artist was shot by radical feminist Valerie Solanas, which may have contributed to his death nineteen years later. In 2013, this artist’s Silver Car Crash (Double Disaster) sold for $105 million. This artist’s Factory in New York City hosted a film studio, an assembly line for lithograph and silk-screening production, and drug-fueled parties featuring celebrities and free-thinkers. For ten points, name this pop artist best known for his Marilyn Diptych and depictions of Campbell’s Soup Cans.",
      "answer": "Andy Warhol"
    },
    {
      "question": "One candidate in this presidential election year secured nomination on the second ballot after the withdrawal of Samuel J. Randall. This was the first election year during which Belva Lockwood appeared on the ballot. The rallying cry \"Burn this letter\" during this election year was popularized after a discovery of some papers by James Mulligan. The slogan \"Ma, Ma, Where’s my Pa?\" mocked the philandering of this year's election winner. For ten points, name this election year in which James G. Blaine lost to Grover Cleveland.",
      "answer": "1884"
    },
    {
      "question": "As part of this project, Kevin Kruse wrote a work titled for how one policy “Caused a Traffic Jam.” Jake Silverstein wrote a “clarification” of this project, which was the subject of a proposal by Tom Cotton to ban federal funding to schools that taught it. Nikole Hannah- Jones developed this project, which included pieces on Crispus Attucks and Phillis Wheatley. The arrival of a privateer in colonial Virginia inspired the date that names, for ten points, what ongoing initiative from The New York Times Magazine focusing on slavery’s impact on America?",
      "answer": "The 1619 Project 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "A shield logo representing one of these institutions depicts a set of staples on the right half in honor of its co-founder, Seth Staples. A process called “elenchus” [[eh-LEN- koos]] provided the basis for a practice at these institutions that is often paired with one that relies on casebooks. Plato’s Theaetetus [[thee-ih-TEE-tuss]] may have introduced a method of “argument by refutation” used at these institutions named for Socrates. Moot court competitions are held at, for ten points, what educational institutions at which students prepare for the bar exam?",
      "answer": "Law schools"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man was killed in Chicago in 1969, one group went on a bombing spree and planned to bomb Fort Dix. The month before his death, this man stated, \"What we’re going to try to do, is we’re going to try to rap and educate\" in a speech about class struggle at Northern Illinois University. After this man's death, Bobby Rush took his former position and said \"we have to arm ourselves.\" William O'Neal drugged this man with barbiturates for the FBI, after which the Chicago police killed him and Mark Clark. For ten points, name this Black Panther leader.",
      "answer": "Frederick \"Fred\" Hampton"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man saved his wingman, \"Jig Dog\" Ramage [[RAM-uhj]], while serving as a fighter pilot. NASA presents an annual Technology in Education Award named for this man. This man was part of a group including Wally Schirra and Deke Slayton and followed Yuri Gagarin in a feat on the Freedom 7, part of the Redstone 3 mission. The oldest man to walk on the moon as part of the Apollo 14 mission, this man hit two golf balls on the moon. The head of the first crewed Project Mercury flight, for ten points, who was this astronaut, the first American to travel into space?",
      "answer": "Alan Shepard"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's assassination in Prague was the subject of a film co-written by Bertolt Brecht and Fritz Lang titled Hangmen Also Die!. This man implemented the Einsatzgruppen mobile death trucks, and he ran the death camp at Chelmno [[HELM-noh]]. This \"Blonde Beast\" called a meeting during which Adolf Eichmann created a list of Jews in various countries. This official organized the Wannsee [[VAHN-zay]] Conference, which united the German bureaucratic branches behind the Final Solution. For ten points, name this commander of the SS, the architect of the Holocaust.",
      "answer": "Reinhard Heydrich 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Historian Ben Kiernan, who studied the abuses of this regime, estimates that between 1.67 and 1.87 million people died as a result of its genocidal policies. In 1975, this regime seized the U.S. merchant vessel SS Mayaguez. This political regime’s Standing Committee included Brother Number Two and Brother Number Three, both of whom were later convicted by a UN tribunal for crimes against humanity. For ten points, name this Cambodian political regime supported by the Viet Cong and the Chinese Communist Party, which was led by Pol Pot.",
      "answer": [
        "Khmer Rouge",
        "Democratic Kampuchea",
        "Communist Party of Cambodia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "On the first day of this event, the leader of the Escambray Rebellion was captured and immediately executed. In preparation for this event, the failed Operation Puma was meant to destroy the armed aircraft of the FAR. This event took place mostly on Girón [[hee- ROHN]] Beach and was executed by Brigade 2506, composed of exiles who intended to overthrow Fidel Castro. For ten points, name this failed 1961 landing operation, covertly supported by the Kennedy administration.",
      "answer": [
        "Bay of Pigs Invasion",
        "Invasión de Bahía de Cochinos",
        "also",
        "Invasión de Playa Girón",
        "Batalla de Girón before \"Girón\" is mentioned 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A legend of these people told of how the captured Emperor Valens was burned in a farmhouse by their men during the Battle of Adrianople. A man descended from this tribe, Pelayo [[peh-LAI-oh]], was victorious at the Battle of Covadonga and ruled the last Iberian kingdom to hold out against the Umayyads. This tribe, which converted to Arianism, faced an attack from the forces of Emperor Honorius, culminating in the 410 Sack of Rome. For ten points, name this Gothic tribe led by King Alaric I, which conquered much of France and Spain.",
        "answer": "Visigoths"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This “Great” emperor of Rome, who made peace with the Visigoths, later made Christianity the official state religion.",
        "answer": "Theodosius the Great or Theodosius I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This American military award was given posthumously to a set of three nurses that included Jane Rignel. In the order of precedence, this military decoration is between the Defense Superior Service Medal and the Distinguished Service Medal. This award was established in 1918 as a successor to the similarly-shaped “Citation” variety. For ten points, name this military decoration awarded for \"gallantry in action\" which, despite its name, is mostly gold.",
        "answer": "Silver Star Medal or SSM"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This United States Army general won three Silver Stars and two Purple Hearts while serving in Vietnam. He led all coalition forces in the Gulf War.",
        "answer": "\"Stormin'\" Norman Schwarzkopf"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This novel was its author's first published work after she quit working for the British Overseas Airways Corporation. In this novel, Dolphus Raymond pretends to drink alcohol while keeping Coca-Cola in a paper bag to fit in with the African-American community. A monument to a character in this novel stands in Monroeville, Alabama, which may have inspired its setting of Maycomb. In this novel, Bob Ewell’s abuse of his daughter is revealed during a trial by Atticus Finch. A girl nicknamed Scout narrates, for ten points, what Harper Lee novel dealing with racial inequality?",
        "answer": "To Kill a Mockingbird"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Monroeville is also known as the hometown of this author and childhood friend of Harper Lee who wrote Breakfast at Tiffany’s and served as the inspiration for Dill in To Kill a Mockingbird.",
        "answer": "Truman Capote 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man invented the heliotrope to carry out a geodetic survey of the Kingdom of Hanover. Wilhelm Weber [[VEH-buh]] and this man constructed the first electromechanical telegraph. This man became the first to prove the quadratic reciprocity law, and in his PhD thesis, this man showed that all polynomials of order \"n\" have \"n\" roots, proving the fundamental theorem of algebra. For ten points, name this German mathematician from Brunswick who names the normal distribution.",
        "answer": "Carl Friedrich Gauss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gauss proved a number of theorems by this French mathematician, including his polygonal number theorem for \"n equals 3.\" The Taniyama-Shimura conjecture was applied to Andrew Wiles's proof of a theorem by this man which went unproven for 358 years.",
        "answer": [
          "Pierre de Fermat ]",
          "pronunciation as ]"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite its opponent being assisted by Ampud and Leustach Rátót, this empire still won the Battle of Myriokephalon [[meer-ee-oh-KEHF-ah-lahn]]. During a march to Khorasan, the Ghaznavid army was constantly attacked by forces of this empire that won the Battle of Dandanaqan [[dahn-DAHN-uh-kun]]. Omar Khayyam served this empire, which oversaw the capture of Romanos IV Diogenes [[dai-AH-jin-ees]]. The Sultanate of Rum [[ROOM]] was an offshoot of this empire, which practiced Sunni Islam. One of the emirates into which this empire was broken served as the basis for the Ottomans. For ten points, name this medieval Anatolian empire.",
        "answer": "Great Seljuk Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Seljuk sultan, the great-grandson of Seljuk himself, won the Battle of Manzikert, captured Romanos IV, and became known by a name which means \"Heroic Lion\" in Turkish.",
        "answer": "Alp Arslan"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After serving for a year with the Light Cavalry in Algeria, this man contracted typhoid fever, left the military, and became a student of Charles Gleyre. As a boy in Le Havre [[luh HAHV]], this man studied with Jacques-François Ochard [[oh-SHARD]]. Eugène Boudin [[yoo-ZHEN boo-DAHN]] taught this man the \"en plein air\" [[OHN PLEHN-AIR]] technique. In 1865, this man created a large, clothed version of Manet's Le déjeuner sur l'herbe [[luh deh-zhuh-NEH soor LEHRB]] but spent many years facing rejection from the Salon de Paris. In 1874, this man and his fellow rejected painters began the Salon des Refusés [[reh-fyoo- SEH]]. For ten points, name this painter of Impression, Sunrise?",
        "answer": "Claude Monet ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As a student in Paris, Monet became friends with this fellow Impressionist, the father of noted film director Jean, and creator of the painting Luncheon of the Boating Party.",
        "answer": "Pierre-Auguste Renoir ] 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This modern-day country's territories were made independent from Venice in the Treaty of Zadar. The second-largest city in this country was surveyed by Robert Adam in his studies of the ruins of Diocletian's Palace. This country's coastline was the location of the Republic of Ragusa, based out of Dubrovnik, and the Greek colony named Aspálathos is today known as this country's city, Split. For ten points, name this country whose war of independence from 1991 to 1995 is known by natives as the \"Greater Serbian Aggression.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Croatia or Republika Hrvatska",
          "Kingdom of Croatia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1809, the territory of modern Croatia was annexed into the First French Empire following the Battle of Wagram during this war in which Austria was supported by a group of nations including the U.K., Portugal, Spain, Sardinia, and Sicily.",
        "answer": "War of the Fifth Coalition"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man argued that excluding groups from the ballot in a democracy branded those groups with the “stigma of inferiority.” In one speech, this man asked if the “principles…embodied in that Declaration of Independence are extended to” the central group and claimed that the Constitution did not intend one practice to be a “gateway.” This man, who asked “What to the Slave is the Fourth of July?\" followed up his best known book with a sequel titled My Bondage and My Freedom. For ten points, name this abolitionist and author of a widely-read \"slave narrative.\"",
        "answer": "Frederick Douglass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1872, Frederick Douglass became the first African-American to be nominated for vice president after this Equal Rights Party candidate nominated him without his approval.",
        "answer": "Victoria Woodhull"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Regarding the U.S. state of Georgia, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the u.s. state of georgia, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sports organization whose Braves moved to Atlanta from Milwaukee in 1966.",
          "answer": [
            "MLB",
            "Major League Baseball"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Federal agency that is headquartered in Georgia and originally focused on malaria control.",
          "answer": [
            "Centers for Disease Control and Prevention",
            "CDC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Freedom Rider and Georgia congressman who helped organize the 1963 March on Washington.",
          "answer": "John Lewis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Speaker of the House from Georgia who co-authored the Contract with America.",
          "answer": "Newt Gingrich"
        },
        {
          "question": "Christian Identity terrorist who bombed the 1996 Olympic games in Atlanta.",
          "answer": "Eric Rudolph"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vice president of the Confederacy and governor of Georgia who popularized the Lost Cause mythology.",
          "answer": "Alexander Stephens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of Georgia during the Civil War where Henry Slocum unofficially voted the state back into the Union.",
          "answer": "Milledgeville"
        },
        {
          "question": "18th Century scandal in which sections of Alabama and Mississippi were sold by Georgia politicians.",
          "answer": [
            "Yazoo land scandal",
            "\"Fraud\"",
            "\"Controversy\" in place of \"Scandal\" 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Islamic Spain",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Peninsula of Spain which Muslim armies conquered in the 8th century.",
          "answer": "Iberian Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medieval hero who fought for both Christians and Muslims, later starting his own state in Valencia.",
          "answer": [
            "El Cid",
            "Rodrigo Díaz de Vivar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Palace in Granada that names a decree issued by the Spanish forcing Jews to convert to Christianity.",
          "answer": "Alhambra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the state of Al-Andalus, known for its architecture at sites like the Alcazar.",
          "answer": "Córdoba"
        },
        {
          "question": "General Arabic word for \"Civil Strife,\" which names the collapse of Al-Andalus in the early 11th century.",
          "answer": "Fitnas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Independent Muslim states in Medieval Spain.",
          "answer": "Taifas ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Andalusian doctor who made strides in birthgiving techniques as court physician of Al-Hakam II.",
          "answer": [
            "Al-Zahrawi",
            "Abulcasis"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Berber sultanate which, from its base in Morocco, launched a 14th-century invasion of southern Spain.",
          "answer": [
            "Marinid Sultanate",
            "Marinids",
            "Marinid Dynasty 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Doctors Without Borders",
      "prompt": "Concerning the organization Doctors Without Borders, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Central American nation which was the site of one of their first missions after an earthquake in Managua.",
          "answer": "Republic of Nicaragua or República de Nicaragua"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prize given by a Norwegian committee which they won in 1999.",
          "answer": "Nobel Peace Prize"
        },
        {
          "question": "African nation whose Biafran War inspired their establishment.",
          "answer": "Republic of Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where both they and the International Red Cross are headquartered.",
          "answer": "Geneva"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nation where their people were arrested after demanding documents about the Janjaweed atrocities in Darfur.",
          "answer": "Republic of the Sudan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Somali militant group whose constant raids forced them to pull out of the region in 2013.",
          "answer": [
            "Harakat Al-Shabaab al Mujahideen",
            "HSM"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Site of a 1995 massacre of 8,000 Bosniak men by Serbs, shortly after they were kicked out of the city.",
          "answer": "Srebrenica ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "African nation whose 2019 landslides in Bujumbura led to an MSF mission being deployed.",
          "answer": "Republic of Burundi or Repubulika y’u Burundi 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Riots erupted after the Treaty of Northampton promised the transfer of this object between two locations. In some stories, this object was used as a pillow by Jacob when he dreamed of a ladder that ascended to heaven. Kenneth MacAlpin brought this item from (20 pts)",
        "Iona [[ai-OH-nah]] to a location from which it was seized by Edward I in 1296. The most recent use of this object in its best known capacity occurred in 1953. Now found in (10 pts)",
        "Edinburgh Castle, this object is fixed to the base of a wooden Coronation Chair. For ten points, name this rock upon which Scottish monarchs have been crowned."
      ],
      "answer": "Stone of Scone ]"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) People who engaged in this practice led a 1939 roadside demonstration in southeast Missouri under Owen Whitfield. This practice, which may have arisen in Adams County, Mississippi, was often accompanied by providing a portion of products as a (20 pts)",
        "lien, creating a cycle of debt. Mules were often rented out for this activity, which became the primary occupation of (10 pts)",
        "African-Americans in the South after the Civil War. For ten points, name this practice in which landowners took a portion of a worker’s harvest in exchange for allowing them to work the land."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sharecropping",
        "Sharecroppers",
        "Tenant Farming",
        "Tenant Farmers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man engaged in an extensive feud over the nature of scientific experiments with Robert Boyle, and in his old age, this Englishman translated Thucydides. A crozier and a sword are held by a king comprised of human bodies in the frontispiece of a work by this man, which claims there is a single (20 pts)",
        "“rule of nature” and originated the idea of the “Kingdom of Darkness.” That work by this man claims that life without law would be (10 pts)",
        "“nasty, brutish, and short.” For ten points, name this political philosopher who wrote Leviathan."
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas Hobbes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The decision that led to this dispute arose from “the first news” William Dickey received after returning from a gold prospecting effort along the Susitna River. A 2015 decision announced by Sally Jewel that aimed to end this dispute was criticized by Donald Trump as “a great insult to (20 pts)",
        "Ohio,” in reference to an earlier president. This dispute has involved the usage of a Koyukon term translating to “the (10 pts)",
        "high One.” Concerning a location containing the Kahiltna glacier, for ten points, what is this dispute over how to refer to a certain Alaska mountain?"
      ],
      "answer": "Denali-Mount McKinley naming dispute 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This event occurred at 4 a.m. local time in order to appear at 10 p.m. in the eastern United States. This event was held in a stadium originally named for King Baudouin [[boh-DWAHN]]. Zack Clayton refereed this event, which was the subject of the film (*) When We Were Kings. The rope-a-dope strategy was employed during this event, which occurred under the auspices of (*) Mobutu Sese Seko. Culminating in an eighth-round knockout of George Foreman, for ten points, what 1974 fight ended with a Muhammad Ali victory in what is now the Democratic Republic of the Congo?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "The Rumble in the Jungle",
        "descriptive answers of Muhammad Ali's victory over George Foreman in the Republic of Zaire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this campaign, Raizo Tanaka sunk a destroyer with a Long Lance at Lunga Point. A nighttime delivery service during this campaign known as “rat transportation” travelled through a location referred to as \"the Slot.\" Also known as Operation (20 pts)",
        "Watchtower, this campaign involved several battles fought around Savo Island. Lofton Henderson became the namesake of an airfield captured during this campaign before it was turned into (10 pts)",
        "Honiara Airport. For ten points, name this World War Two campaign fought in the Solomon Islands."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Guadalcanal Campaign",
        "Battle of Guadalcanal",
        "Operation Watchtower before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Death squads targeting this group, known as the GAL, conducted the Monbar Hotel attack and murdered Lasa and Zabala. This organization was targeted in the 1970 Burgos trials which received international condemnation after six members of this group were (20 pts)",
        "sentenced to death. Members of this group packed Goma-2 explosives under a street, which exploded when Luis Carrero Blanco's Dart arrived in an act codenamed Operation (10 pts)",
        "Ogre. This group used the motto \"Keep up on both\" and allied with the Batasuna party. For ten points, name this Basque terrorist group."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ETA",
        "Euskadi Ta Askatasuna"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The song “Copper Kettle” references this event, which included the Battle of Bower Hill. Riots in Hagerstown cascaded into Carlisle during this event, in which the slogan (20 pts)",
        "“Liberty or Death” was raised on a number of poles. Albert Gallatin regretted attending a meeting in Monongahela with leading members of this event. “Light-Horse” Harry Lee helped put down this event, which followed a similar event led by Daniel (10 pts)",
        "Shays. For ten points, name this revolt against an excise tax on alcohol."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Whiskey Rebellion",
        "synonyms for \"Rebellion\" such as \"Insurrection\"",
        "\"Revolt\" 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 5"
      ]
    }
  ]
}